Register of the Henry Franklin Gadsby papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Henry Franklin Gadsby papers
1897-1949
1915-1940
78096
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes, 7 oversized boxes (14.6 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, printed matter, and memorabilia relating to Canadian and British politics, primarily in the inter-war period, and to British Empire war efforts during World War I.
Gadsby, Henry Franklin, 1869-1951
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1978.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Henry Franklin Gadsby was born in St. Catharines, Ontario in 1869. In 1889, he graduated from the University of Toronto and became a journalist. Gadsby had an illustrious fifty-year literary career span as a liberal political satirist examining Canadian and British parliamentary politics and the Home Rule struggle in Ireland during the inter-war period. He was a feature writer for the Montreal Standard, Toronto Saturday Night, and the Toronto Star and a frequent free-lance contributor to various other Canadian and US newspapers and magazines. In the early 1920s, Gadsby served as president of the Parlimentary Press Gallery in Ottawa. In addition, he was a war correspondent during the Boer War, Mexican War, and World War I. Though known for his humorist satires, Gadsby was also a poet and playwright. Gadsby died in 1951.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Henry Franklin Gadsby papers document his literary career as a political satirist, poet, and war correspondent through correspondence, manuscripts, and his published works.
The collection is arranged into five series: Biographical File, Correspondence, Writings, Subject File, and Printed Matter. The Biographical File is comprised of personal identification cards, family documents, biographical sketches, and press mentions of Gadsby. Correspondence mainly reflects Gadsby’s professional relationships with the House of Commons, Office of the Prime Minister, and various editorial and publishing organizations. Writings consists of manuscripts and published works, mainly Gadsby’s political satire columns in the Montreal Standard, Toronto Saturday Night and the Toronto Star. The Subject File predominantly focuses on Gadsby’s association with the Press Gallery and research materials relating to the Canadian Military, including pamphlets, correspondence, and manuscripts.The remainder of the collection is Printed Matter, which consists mainly of travel mementos such as booklets, maps, and travels guides; also included is a scrapbook of poems, news clippings, and notes.
Canada--Politics and government--1914-1945.; Canada.; Great Britain--Politics and government--1910-1936.; Journalists.; King, William Lyon Mackenzie, -- 1874-1950.; Political satire.; World War, 1914-1918--Great Britain
- Biographical File, 1912-1949
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains identification records, news clippings, photographs, invitations, membership records, and family documents that detail Gadsby’s personal life and participation in various associations. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Biographical sketches, 1943-1949 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Family records, undated (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Farmhouse records, 1937-1949 (Box-folder 1:3-4)
  - Invitations, 1918-1932 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - National Liberal Club membership, 1912-1918 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Passport and national registration, 1918, 1942 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Photographs of family, 1920s (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Press mentions, undated (Box-folder 1:9)
  - University of Toronto alumni activities, 1935-1949 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Correspondence, 1908-1949
  Contains letters received from associates and colleagues, mainly regarding Gadsby's literary endeavors. Arranged chronologically, then by organization or topic.
  - General correspondence, 1909-1949, undated
    - 1909 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - 1915 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2:3)
    - 1920-1929 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - 1930-1935 (Box-folder 2:5)
    - 1937-1944 (Box-folder 2:6)
    - 1949 (Box-folder 2:7)
    - undated (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Office of the Prime Minister, 1908-1947 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Editors and publishers, 1910-1949 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - House of Commons, 1913-1934 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Syndicate, 1915 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Canadian National Railways and Canadian Pacific Railway Company, 1921-1933 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - The American Universities Club of London, undated (Box-folder 2:14)
- Writings, 1912-1949
  Contains notebooks, research notes, manuscripts, and published works that relate to Canadian political events and Gadsby's personal poetry. Most of the works are articles he wrote for the Montreal Standard, Toronto Saturday Night, and the Toronto Star. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Article sketches, notes, and parliamentary meeting notebooks, undated (Box-folder 3:1-2)
  - "Articles to Work Over,", undated (Box-folder 3:3)
  - "As Things May Go in 1960," draft, Montreal Standard, 1930s (Box-folder 3:4)
  - "At the Interpreter's House, with Apologies to John Buryan," draft, undated (Box-folder 3:5)
  - "Camel's Back,", undated (Box-folder 3:6)
  - "Canada's Wonder Day," draft, undated (Box-folder 3:7)
  - "Chromatic" column, Evening Star, 1897-1898 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - "Description of the House of Commons," draft, 1933 May 23 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - "The Devil and The Deep Sea,” draft, undated (Box-folder 3:10)
  - "Diary of a Back Bencher," drafts, undated (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Edits to articles, drafts, 1915-1945 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - "For the Weeklies,", undated (Box-folder 4:2)
  - "Gadsby Letters (England)," drafts, 1912 October-1913 January (Box-folder 4:3)
  - "Gallery Clock" column, Toronto Star, 1900-1912 (Box 8)
  - "Gallery Clock" column, Toronto Star, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - "If Jesus Came to Ottawa,” draft, circa 1943 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - "It's Always Fair Weather When Good Fellows Get Together," draft, undated (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Joseph Discovered by His Brethen, 1917 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - The King's Flagon, 1899 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - "The Man from the Moon: An Allegory," draft, undated (Box-folder 4:9)
  - "The Man in Charge,” draft, undated (Box-folder 4:10)
  - "Man of July," draft, undated (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Montreal Standard articles, 1920-1938 (Box 9-14)
  - Notes, undated (Box-folder 4:12)
  - "One Complex Too Many,” draft, 1940s (Box-folder 4:13)
  - "Page Colonel Mellows for Me,” draft, undated (Box-folder 4:14)
  - "Parlimentary Sketches," drafts, 1913 April 29 (Box-folder 4:15)
  - "The Past Is Over Our Shoulder, draft, undated (Box-folder 4:16)
  - Poems, Canadian Magazine, circa 1898 (Box-folder 4:17)
  - Poems, jokes, and sketches, undated (Box-folder 5:1)
  - "Power of the Press, An Imaginary Conversation,” draft, undated (Box-folder 5:2)
  - "Quebec and the Draft," Century Magazine, circa 1898 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - "Richard the Fourth, King of Canada," drafts, undated (Box-folder 5:4)
  - "The Sample Seven Doing Their Bit: Gadsby on Parlimentary Colonels," Ottawa Free Press, undated (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Saturday Night magazine articles, 1914-1919 (Box 8)
  - "Scare the Wealth Gets Together," draft, undated (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Speech notes on journalism, undated (Box-folder 5:7)
  - "Totem Pole Decoration for Chateau Laurien Tea Garden: An Indian Allegorization of Canada's History from 1867-1928,", undated (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Untitled manuscripts, 1914 (Box-folder 5:9-10)
  - War syndicate proofs Nos. 2-11, 1918-1919 (Box 8)
  - "When Deep Calls on the Deep, draft, undated (Box-folder 5:11)
  - "When None for the Party," draft, 1930s (Box-folder 5:12)
  - "Why Good Advice Goes Wrong," draft, 1930s (Box-folder 5:13)
  - "Wind in the Mulberry," draft, undated (Box-folder 5:14)
  - "WLO Makes Its Bid," draft, undated (Box-folder 5:15)
- Subject File, 1908-1938
  Contains drafts, pamphlets, booklets, and correspondence regarding Gadsby's research and association with the Press Gallery. Arranged chronologically.
  - Quebec Battlefield Association, 1908-1910 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Mexican War travel documentation, 1914 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - World War I military manuals and research notes, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Parliamentary Press Gallery, 1922-1938 (Box-folder 6:4-5)
- Printed Matter, 1906-1930s
  Includes a scrapbook, booklets, travel guides, and maps. Arranged by format and subject.
  - Travel documents and mementos, 1906-1930's (Box-folder 6:6-8)
  - Writers' guides, dictionaries, pamphlets, and ephemera, circa 1910-1930 (Box-folder 7:1-2)
  - Scrapbook of news clippings, undated (Box 7)
    Contains newspaper clippings, manuscripts, and notes.